## **Emily Wall**

My research involves decision making using data visualizations and visual analytics. I develop computational strategies to characterize human limitations in decision making (e.g., cognitive bias) and design interventions to promote reflective data analysis and decision making processes.

I will be joining the Department of Computer Science at Emory University as an Assistant Professor in Summer 2021. I am currently completing a Postdoc at Northwestern University with Jessica Hullman and Steve Franconeri (2020 - 2021). I completed my Ph.D. in Computer Science at Georgia Tech in 2020.

■ emily.wall@emory.edu 🖙 Google Scholar

emilywall.github.io in LinkedIn

# **Appointments**

2021- Assistant Professor

Department of Computer Science

**Emory University** 

2020-2021 Postdoctoral Researcher

Department of Computer Science

Northwestern University

## **Education**

2020 Ph.D. in Computer Science

Georgia Institute of Technology

Thesis: Detecting and Mitigating Human Bias in Visual Analytics

Committee: Alex Endert, John Stasko, Polo Chau, Brian Fisher, Wenwen Dou

2015 B.S. in Computer Science & Mathematics

University of Georgia summa cum laude

# **Honors & Awards**

2020 VGTC Best Dissertation, Honorable Mention

2019 **GVU Foley Scholar**, Recipient, Georgia Institute of Technology

2019	D.E. Shaw Exploration Fellowship, Recipient
2019-2020	Siemens FutureMaker Fellowship, Recipient
2018	GVU Foley Scholar, Finalist, Georgia Institute of Technology
2017	Graduate Student Symposium, Participant, AT&T Labs
2017	Doctoral Colloquium, Participant, IEEE VIS
2017-2020	Graduate Fellowship for STEM Diversity (GFSD), Recipient
2017	NSF Graduate Research Fellowship Program, Honorable Mention
2017	Department of Defense SMART Fellowship, Recipient (Declined)
2015-2019	President's Fellowship, Recipient, Georgia Institute of Technology
2015	CURO Symposium Best Paper Award, University of Georgia
2014	CURO Research Assistantship, University of Georgia
2014	Hahn Family Scholarship for Computer Science, Recipient, University of
	Georgia
2013	Hollingsworth Award for Excellence in Mathematics, Recipient, University of
	Georgia
2012-2015	Zell Miller Scholarship, Recipient, University of Georgia

### **Publications**

### **Journal Articles**

#### A Heuristic Approach to Value-Driven Evaluation of Visualizations

E. Wall, M. Agnihotri, L. Matzen, K. Divis, M. Haass, A. Endert, and J. Stasko *IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics (Proc. InfoVis'18)*, 2019.

🖺 PDF | 🖽 Talk | 🏶 Website | 🕪 Video FF

### Podium: Ranking Data Using Mixed-Initiative Visual Analytics

E. Wall, S. Das, R. Chawla, B. Kalidindi, E. Brown, and A. Endert IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics (Proc. VAST'17), 2018.

🖺 PDF | 🖽 Talk | 🏲 Video | 🛏 Video FF | 💂 Demo

### AxiSketcher: Interactive Nonlinear Axis Mapping of Visualizations through User Drawings

B.C. Kwon, H. Kim, *E. Wall*, J. Choo, H. Park, and A. Endert

IEEE Transactions on Visualization and Computer Graphics (Proc. VAST'16), 2017.

 PDF |

 Video

### **Conference Proceedings**

### Toward a Design Space for Mitigating Cognitive Bias in Vis

E. Wall, J. Stasko, and A. Endert

IEEE Information Visualization (VIS) Short Papers, 2019.

🖺 PDF | 🖿 Supplemental | 🖽 Talk | 🍽 Video FF

### A Markov Model of Users' Interactive Behavior in Scatterplots

E. Wall, A. Arcalgud, K. Gupta, and A. Jo

IEEE Information Visualization (VIS) Short Papers, 2019.

 PDF | ⊞ Talk | ▶ Video FF

### A Formative Study of Interactive Bias Metrics in Visual Analytics Using Anchoring Bias

E. Wall, L. Blaha, C. Paul, and A. Endert

Proceedings of the 17th IFIP TC 13 International Conference on Human-Computer Interaction (INTERACT'19), 2019.

PDF | ▶ Video

# Using Expert Patterns in Assisted Interactive Machine Learning: A Study in Machine Teaching

E. Wall, S. Ghorashi, and G. Ramos

Proceedings of the 17th IFIP TC 13 International Conference on Human-Computer Interaction (INTERACT'19), 2019.

PDF | ▶ Video

# Warning, Bias May Occur: A Proposed Approach to Detecting Cognitive Bias in Interactive Visual Analytics

E. Wall, L. Blaha, L. Franklin, and A. Endert

IEEE Visual Analytics Science and Technology (VAST), 2017.

 PDF | 目 Talk | ▶ Video | ▶ Video FF

#### Supporting Team-First Visual Analytics through Group Activity Representations

S.K. Badam, Z. Zeng, *E. Wall*, A. Endert, and N. Elmqvist *Graphics Interface*, 2017.

 PDF | ▶ Video

### **Workshop Papers**

#### COVID-19 Health Equity Dashboard - Addressing Vulnerable Populations

S. Liu, E. Wall, S. Patel, and Y. Park

Visualization for Communication (VisComm, at VIS'20), 2020.

PDF

### Four Perspectives on Human Bias in Visual Analytics

E. Wall, L. Blaha, C. Paul, K. Cook, and A. Endert

DECISIVe: Workshop on Dealing with Cognitive Biases in Visualizations (at InfoVis'17), 2017.

₽DF

### **Book Chapters**

#### Four Perspectives on Human Bias in Visual Analytics

E. Wall, L. Blaha, C. Paul, K. Cook, and A. Endert

Cognitive Biases in Visualizations, Ed. G. Ellis, Springer, 2018, Chapter 3, pp. 29-42.

■ Book | ■ Chapter

#### **Theses**

### **Detecting and Mitigating Human Bias in Visual Analytics**

Emily Wall

Georgia Tech, School of Interactive Computing Ph.D. Thesis. April 2020.



# **Professional Experience**

2015-2020 Georgia Institute of Technology, Atlanta, GA

Graduate Research Assistant Advised by Dr. Alex Endert

Thesis: Detecting and Mitigating Human Bias in Visual Analytics

Summer Microsoft Research, Redmond, WA
2018 Intern, Machine Teaching Group

Mentored by Dr. Gonzalo Ramos

Modeled how experts use machine teaching to train ML classifiers. Developed

systematic guidelines to help novices train ML classifiers.

Summer Pacific Northwest National Laboratory, Richland, WA

<sup>2016</sup> Intern, Visual Analytics Group

Mentored by Lyndsey Franklin and Kris Cook

Developed heuristics to characterize bias in real-time from user interaction

sequences

2013-2015 Jet Propulsion Laboratory, Pasadena, CA

Intern, Systems Engineering Group

Advised by Marc Sarrel

Used SysML and principles of Model-Based Systems Engineering to visualize

network flows for Lockheed Martin's Orion capsule

Fall 2014 University of Georgia, Athens, GA

Undergraduate Research Assistant

Advised by Dr. Don Potter

Developed neural network to predict solar radiation in Georgia; funded by the

Georgia Power Advanced Solar Initiative

Fall 2013 University of Georgia, Athens, GA

Undergraduate Research Assistant

Advised by Dr. Liming Cai

Used sequence alignment techniques to determine coevolution of species with

a common ancestor

Spring 2013 University of Georgia, Athens, GA

Undergraduate Research Assistant

Advised by Dr. Prashant Doshi

Created simulation and programmable interface for Parrot A.R. Drone

quadcopters to serve as a testbed for autonomous decision making with UAVs

# **Grants & Funding**

2019-2020 Toward Mitigating Cognitive Bias for Data-Driven Decision Making with Visual

**Analytics** 

Siemens FutureMaker Fellowship

Co-Pls: <u>Dr. Alex Endert</u> Funded: \$101,435

2019 Detecting and Mitigating Human Bias in Visual Analytics

GVU Foley Scholar
Co-Pls: Dr. Alex Endert
Funded: \$5,000

2017-2020 Toward Mitigating Cognitive Bias for Data-Driven Decision-Making With

**Visual Analytics** 

Graduate Fellowship for STEM Diversity (GFSD)

Co-Pls: Dr. Alex Endert

Funded: \$20,000 / year for 3 years

2014 Predicting Solar Radiation in Georgia

CURO Research Assistantship

Co-Pls: <u>Dr. Don Potter</u> Funded: \$1,000

# **Teaching**

### **Teaching Assistant**

Spring Introduction to Information Visualization (CS 4460) (133 students)

2019 Georgia Institute of Technology

Fall 2017 Information Visualization (CS 7450) (74 students)

Georgia Institute of Technology

Fall 2013 Introduction to Computing and Programming (CSCI 1301)

University of Georgia

Fall 2012 Introduction to Computing and Programming (CSCI 1301)

University of Georgia

#### **Guest Lectures**

Feb 2019 Introduction to Javascript

Introduction to Information Visualization (CS 4460), Georgia Institute of

Technology

Dec 2017 Cognition in Visualization

Information Visualization (CS 7450), Georgia Institute of Technology

Nov 2017 **Visual Analytics** 

Information Visualization (CS 7450), Georgia Institute of Technology

Introduction to Information Visualization (CS 4460), Georgia Institute of Technology

### **Presentations**

### **Invited Talks**

### As We Are: Detecting and Mitigating Human Bias in Visual Analytics

- > April 2021. University of Utah, Data Science Seminar. Virtual Seminar.
- > October 2020. Pacific Northwest National Laboratory. Virtual Brown Bag.
- > September 2020. Emory University. Atlanta, GA. 🔁 Abstract
- > May 2020. CMU & AFRL, Center for Excellence on Human-Machine Teaming. Virtual Brown Bag.
- > May 2020. Siemens. Virtual Brown Bag.
- > March 2020. Cornell University, Info Science Colloquium. Ithaca, NY. 🛂 Abstract
- > February 2020. University of Washington, Allen School Colloquium. Seattle, WA. 🔄 Watch
- > February 2020. Emory University. Atlanta, GA. 🛂 Abstract
- > February 2020. New York University. New York, NY. 🔄 Abstract
- > February 2020. University of Wisconsin. Madison, WI.

### Left, Right, and Gender: Mitigating Implicit Human Bias in Visual Analytics

> January 2020. Georgia Institute of Technology, GVU Brown Bag. Atlanta, GA. 🛂 Watch

### The Interactive Analytics Library: Treating Interaction as Data

> May 2017. Pacific Northwest National Laboratory. Richland, WA.

### **Posters and Demonstrations**

# Warning, Bias May Occur: Detecting and Mitigating Cognitive Bias in Visual Analytics (Poster & Demo)

- > October 2019. Georgia Institute of Technology, GVU Demo Showcase. Atlanta, GA.
- > June 2019. Summer Institute on Bounded Rationality. Berlin, Germany.
- > April 2019. Georgia Institute of Technology, GVU Demo Showcase. Atlanta, GA.

# Warning, Bias May Occur: A Proposed Approach to Detecting Cognitive Bias in Interactive Visual Analytics (Demo)

- > April 2018. CRA-W Grad Cohort. San Francisco, CA.
- > April 2018. Georgia Institute of Technology, GVU Demo Showcase. Atlanta, GA.
- > April 2017. Georgia Institute of Technology, GVU Demo Showcase. Atlanta, GA.

### Podium: Ranking Data Using Mixed-Initiative Visual Analytics (Poster & Demo)

- > April 2018. Georgia Institute of Technology, GVU Demo Showcase. Atlanta, GA.
- > April 2017. Georgia Institute of Technology, GVU Demo Showcase. Atlanta, GA.
- > April 2018. CRA-W Grad Cohort. San Diego, CA.
- > April 2016. Georgia Institute of Technology, GVU Demo Showcase. Atlanta, GA.

# **Mentoring**

2020-2021	Jenni Hutson, B.A. Computer Science and Radio/TV/Film, Northwestern University, Class of 2021 Developed system for visualization recommendations that support decision making
2020	Star Liu, B.S. Quantitative Sciences, Emory University, Class of 2021 Developed system for visualizing health inequities during the COVID-19 pandemic, first author of case study on COVID-19 Health Equity Dashboard
2020	Jamal Paden, B.S. Computer Science, Georgia Institute of Technology, Class of 2020 Conducted usability testing for bias mitigation interventions
2017-2018	<b>Yingxiao Ouyang</b> , M.S. HCI, Georgia Institute of Technology, Class of 2019 Conducted usability testing and prototyping for bias mitigation interventions <i>Now: UX Designer at Walmart Labs</i>
2017	Qiaochu Mu, M.S. HCl, Georgia Institute of Technology, Class of 2018 Conducted usability testing and prototyping for bias mitigation interventions
2016-2017	Bharath Kalidindi, B.S. Computer Science, Georgia Institute of Technology, Class of 2018  Developed system for ranking data from user interaction, coauthored publication of Podium  Now: Software Engineer at Yahoo

## **Service**

### **Professional Service**

2021 **Organizing Committee**Elections Chair, VIS 2021

> Program Committee Member

IEEE VIS, 2021

IEEE VIS Short Papers, 2020 VISxAI Workshop at IEEE VIS, 2019 CHI Late Breaking Work, 2018

2020-2021 Organizer

TRust and EXpertise in Visual Analytics (TREX) Workshop at IEEE VIS 2021 TRust and EXpertise in Visual Analytics (TREX) Workshop at IEEE VIS 2020

2017 Panelist

Advancing Visualization Inclusion and Diversity (AVID) Workshop at IEEE VIS

> Reviewer

IEEE VIS: 2017-2021 CHI: 2018-2021 TVCG: 2018-2021 EuroVis: 2020-2021 CG&A: 2021 CSCW: 2021

International Journal of Human-Computer Studies: 2019

KDD IDEA: 2017 VAST Challenge: 2016

#### **Institutional Service**

2021 Faculty Search Committee
Computer Science Department, Emory University

2021 Graduate Admissions Committee
Computer Science Department, Emory University

2018-2020 Graduate Student Council Chair, School of Interactive Computing
Representative of graduate students in the School of Interactive Computing

2017-2018 Graduate Student Council Travel Committee
Responsible for reviewing and awarding travel grants to graduate student applicants in the College of Computing

### **Selected Media**

Nov 2019 A Reflection on VIS2019: Or, How Doomed Are We? Medium Blog Post, Multiple Views on Visualization Research Explained. Read by Michael Correll
 Nov 2019 Highlights from IEEE VIS 2019, Uncharted Software Blog. Read by Rosa Romero-Gómez
 May 2019 Battling Bias. Ep. 3, Tech Unbound Podcast. Listen with Josh Preston

## Other Professional Activities

Oct 2019	<b>NextProf Nexus Workshop</b> Atlanta, GA
Jun 2019	<b>Summer Institute on Bounded Rationality</b> Berlin, Germany
Apr 2018	<b>CRA-W Grad Cohort Workshop</b> San Francisco, CA
Oct 2016	<b>Grace Hopper Celebration of Women in Computing</b> Houston, TX
Apr 2016	CRA-W Grad Cohort Workshop San Diego, CA